where we help the communities build latrines, and we teach them to separate their animals from their living quarters in order to reduce the fly population. So we know how to tackle the disease. But we need to know where it is. And we do, because a few years ago, Sightsavers led an incredible program called the Global Trachoma Mapping Project. It took us three years, but we went through 29 countries, and we taught local health workers to go district by district, and they examined the eyelids of over two and a half million people. And they used Android phones in order to download the data. And from that, we were able to build a map that showed us where the disease was. Now, this is a very high-level map that shows you which countries had a problem with trachoma. And you may ask me, "Well, does this strategy actually work?" Yes, it does. This map shows you the progress that we've made to date. The green countries believe they've already eliminated trachoma, and they have either been through or are in the process of having that validated by the WHO. Countries in yellow have the money they need, they have the resources to eliminate trachoma. And some of them are really nearly there. But the red countries, they don't have enough funding. They cannot eliminate trachoma unless they get more. And we're quite concerned, though, that the progress to date may stall. So when we were talking to the Audacious ideas guys, we asked ourselves: If we really, really pushed ourselves over the next four or five years and we had the money, what do we think we could achieve? Well, we believe that we can eliminate trachoma in 12 African countries and across the Americas and all across the Pacific. And we can make significant progress in two countries which have the highest burden of the disease, which is Ethiopia and Nigeria. And in doing all of that, we can leverage more than two billion dollars' worth of donated drugs. (Applause) Now, this map here shows you the impact that we'll have -- look how many countries are going green. And there, you can see progress in Ethiopia and Nigeria. Now, yes, there are some countries that are still red. These are mainly countries which are in conflict -- places like Yemen, South Sudan -- where it's very difficult to work. So, we have the team, the strategy and the map. And we also have the relationships with the governments so that we can make sure that our program is coordinated with other disease-control programs, so that we can be efficient. Wouldn't it be amazing if we could do this? We'd have trachoma on the run. We would be on the home straight to eliminate this disease from the whole world. But before I finish, I just want to share with you some words from the founder of Sightsavers, a guy called Sir John Wilson. Now, he was blinded at the age of 12. And he said, "People don't go blind by the million. They go blind one by one." And in the excitement of being able to say we've got rid of trachoma for the whole country, let's not forget that, actually, this is a devastating disease that destroys the lives of individual people. People like Twiba. Now, I met Twiba last year in Tanzania. She had had trachoma for as long as she could remember. And a couple of months before I met her, she'd had the operation. It's no exaggeration to say that this had totally transformed her life. We'd saved the sight that she had left, and she was free of pain. She could sleep. She could work, she could socialize. And she said to me, "I have my life back." And it was impossible not to be moved by her story. But there are so many Twibas. I want to find all the Twibas, and I don't want anyone to go blind in agony anymore. Now, you know, there are so many intractable problems in this world. But this is not one of them. This is something that we can solve. And we can ensure that kids like this can grow up free from the fear of trachoma. So, for the sake of kids like this, and for the sake of people like Twiba, let's get rid of trachoma. Do you think we can? Well, yeah, if we really, really want to. Yes, we can. So thank you. (Applause)
Ayudamos a las comunidades a construir letrinas, y les enseñamos a separar sus animales de sus viviendas para reducir la cantidad de moscas. Así que sabemos cómo atacar la enfermedad. Pero tenemos que saber dónde está. Y lo sabemos, porque Sightsavers, hace unos años, llevó a cabo un programa increíble que se llamó Proyecto Mundial de Mapeo del Tracoma. Nos llevó tres años, pero fuimos a 29 países, formando trabajadores de la salud locales, que luego fueron distrito por distrito y examinaron los párpados de más de 2,5 millones de personas. Usaron teléfonos Android para descargar los datos. Y a partir de eso pudimos trazar un mapa para ver dónde estaba la enfermedad. Este es un mapa muy general que muestra los países donde el tracoma era endémico. Uds. podrían preguntarme: "¿Funciona realmente esta estrategia?" Sí, funciona. Este mapa muestra el progreso que hemos hecho hasta ahora. Los países en verde consideran que han eliminado el tracoma, y ya han obtenido, o están en proceso de obtener, la validación de la OMS. Los países en amarillo tienen el dinero que necesitan, tienen los recursos para eliminar el tracoma. Y algunos están muy cerca de lograrlo. Pero los países en rojo no tienen suficientes fondos. No pueden eliminar el tracoma a menos que consigan más. Y nos preocupa mucho que se frene el progreso hecho hasta ahora. Entonces, mientras hablábamos con el equipo de Audacious, nos preguntamos: Si nos esforzáramos mucho, pero mucho, durante los próximos cuatro o cinco años, y si tuviéramos el dinero, ¿qué pensamos que podríamos conseguir? Bueno, creemos que podemos eliminar el tracoma en 12 países africanos y en toda América y en todo el Pacífico. Y podemos hacer un progreso importante en los dos países donde la enfermedad pesa más: Etiopía y Nigeria. Y haciendo todo eso, podemos aprovechar más USD 2000 millones en donaciones de medicamentos. (Aplausos) Este mapa les muestra el impacto que vamos a tener... fíjense cuántos países pasaron al verde. Y ahí pueden ver el progreso en Etiopía y en Nigeria. Es verdad, todavía quedan algunos países en rojo. Son principalmente países en conflicto, países como Yemen, Sudán del Sur, donde es muy difícil trabajar. Entonces, tenemos el equipo, la estrategia y el mapa. Y también tenemos los contactos a nivel gubernamental para coordinar nuestro programa con otros programas de control de enfermedades de un modo eficiente. ¿No sería increíble si pudiéramos hacer esto? Tendríamos al tracoma en retirada. Estaríamos en la recta final para eliminar la enfermedad en todo el mundo. Pero, antes de terminar, quisiera compartir con Uds. unas palabras del fundador de Sightsavers, un hombre llamado Sir John Wilson. Él se quedó ciego a los 12 años. Y dijo: "Un millón de personas no se quedan ciegas al mismo tiempo. Se quedan ciegas una por una". Y en el entusiasmo de poder decir que eliminamos el tracoma en todo el país, no nos olvidemos que, en realidad, esta es una enfermedad devastadora que le destruye la vida a cada persona. Personas como Twiba. Conocí a Twiba el año pasado en Tanzania. Ella había tenido tracoma desde que tenía memoria. Y se operó un par de meses antes de que yo la conociera. No exagero cuando digo que la operación le había transformado totalmente la vida. Habíamos salvado la visión que le quedaba y ya no tenía más dolor. Podía dormir. Podía trabajar, podía socializar. Y me dijo: "He recuperado mi vida". Fue imposible no conmoverme con la historia de esa mujer. Pero hay muchas Twibas. Yo quiero encontrar a todas las Twibas, y no quiero que nadie más se quede ciego en el dolor, nunca más. ¿Saben qué? Hay muchos problemas intratables en el mundo. Pero este no es uno de ellos. Esto es algo que podemos solucionar. Y podemos asegurarnos de que niños como estos puedan crecer sin miedo al tracoma. Así que, por los niños como estos, y por las personas como Twiba, eliminemos el tracoma. ¿Piensan que podemos hacerlo? Bueno, si realmente lo queremos, sí. Sí, podemos. Así que gracias. (Aplausos)